<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>formhub blog</title>
 <link href="http://blog.formhub.org/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://blog.formhub.org/"/>
 <updated>2013-04-02T12:07:23+05:30</updated>
 <id>http://blog.formhub.org</id>
 <author>
   <name>formhub blog</name>
 </author>
 
 
 <entry>
   <title>What is formhub? A video.</title>
   <link href="http://blog.formhub.org/2013/02/22/what-is-formhub-a-video"/>
   <updated>2013-02-22T19:38:35+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://blog.formhub.org/2013/02/22/what-is-formhub-a-video</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Want to tell a friend what formhub is, but unable to give them a full demo? Maybe &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jqpmMpkIXSQ&quot;&gt;the following video&lt;/a&gt; will help!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>formhub user's guide</title>
   <link href="http://blog.formhub.org/2013/01/15/formhub-users-guide"/>
   <updated>2013-01-15T19:30:02+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://blog.formhub.org/2013/01/15/formhub-users-guide</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re happy to release a new formhub User&amp;rsquo;s Guide that provides an introductory overview of some of the functionalities formhub provides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script async class=&quot;speakerdeck-embed&quot; data-id=&quot;1a33a070416b01307b8022000a1de118&quot; data-ratio=&quot;1.33333333333333&quot; src=&quot;//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Leigh Jaschke for her help in putting this together!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Account activity log</title>
   <link href="http://blog.formhub.org/2013/01/11/account-activity-log"/>
   <updated>2013-01-11T07:58:41+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://blog.formhub.org/2013/01/11/account-activity-log</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Many data collection projects have strict research protocols on how data can be accessed or modified.  To help with with this, we&amp;rsquo;re excited to announce that we&amp;rsquo;ve added activity/audit logs to formhub.  This allows you to view what actions have been performed on your formhub account, by which user(s) and at what times. To access this log, click on the little arrow next to your username and select &amp;ldquo;Account Activity&amp;rdquo; from the list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Account Activity page&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The activity list has these 4 columns:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Performed On &amp;ndash; The date and time that the action was performed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Action &amp;ndash; The name of the action performed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Performed By &amp;ndash; The username of the user who performed the action&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Description &amp;ndash; A short description of what was exactly done and what it affected&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/2013/01/Screen-Shot-2013-01-15-at-10.35.58-PM.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/2013/01/Screen-Shot-2013-01-15-at-10.35.58-PM.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, the list will display the most recent activity first, this sort order can be changed by clicking on the &amp;ldquo;Performed On&amp;rdquo; column header (or any of the other columns headers to sort by them).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Filtering the activity list&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can perform a filter on the activity list to for example look at any form delete actions. There are two ways to perform filters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Using the general search box labelled &amp;ldquo;Search data&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;. This search looks through each of the fields for whatever you type in. It is fine for a general search but you cannot for example search for actions within a specific time period.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Using the filter box on the right to search through specific fields. This allows you to specify which field to search through and allows you specify strict criteria. E.g. to search for activity between two dates, click on &amp;ldquo;Add Filter&amp;rdquo;, leave the field as &amp;ldquo;Performed On&amp;rdquo; and change type to &lt;strong&gt;Range&lt;/strong&gt; and click &lt;strong&gt;Add&lt;/strong&gt; to add the filter. The &lt;strong&gt;Range&lt;/strong&gt; filter type allows you to specify the start and end values of the range via the &lt;strong&gt;From&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;To &lt;/strong&gt;fields. Clicking on either will display a date picker that would allow you to specify the date. As of this writing, you will have to specify the time by typing it in manually. Click on &amp;ldquo;Update&amp;rdquo; to apply the filter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The filter can also be used to search for specific actions from a list of pre-defined actions. To do this, start by clicking on &amp;ldquo;Add Filter.&amp;rdquo; Change the field to &amp;ldquo;Actions&amp;rdquo; and the filter type to &amp;ldquo;Options&amp;rdquo; and add the filter. This will display a dropdown with the list of available action types as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;public-profile-accessed &amp;ndash; When the account&amp;rsquo;s profile is accessed by anyone other then the owner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;profile-settings-updated &amp;ndash; When the account&amp;rsquo;s settings are updated&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bulk-submissions-made &amp;ndash; When a bulk submission is made to the account&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;form-accessed &amp;ndash; When a form on the account is accessed. The description will include the name of the form&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;form-published &amp;ndash; When a form is published&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;form-updated &amp;ndash; When a form&amp;rsquo;s seetings are updated, the description will include which settings were updated and what the values were changed to&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;form-xls-downloaded &amp;ndash; When the source XLS file is downloaded&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;form-xls-updated &amp;ndash; When an existing form&amp;rsquo;s XLS is updated&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;form-deleted &amp;ndash; When a form is deleted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;form-cloned &amp;ndash; When a form is cloned&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;form-permissions-updated &amp;ndash; When the form&amp;rsquo;s sharing permissions are updated&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;form-enter-data-requested &amp;ndash; When the web form entry is initiated&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;form-map-viewed &amp;ndash; When the form page is opened&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;form-data-viewed &amp;ndash; When the form&amp;rsquo;s data is viewed through the various web views&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;export-created &amp;ndash; When an export is created&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;export-downloaded &amp;ndash; When an export is downloaded&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;export-deleted &amp;ndash; When an export is deleted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;submission-created &amp;ndash; When a submission is made&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;submission-deleted &amp;ndash; When a submission is deleted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;submission-edit-requested &amp;ndash; When a submission edit is requested. When the edit is complete, it will be logged as a submission-created&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bamboo-link-created &amp;ndash; A link to the bamboo service is created&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bamboo-link-deleted &amp;ndash; A link to the bamboo service is deleted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Building Capacity for Energy Planning in Liberia with formhub</title>
   <link href="http://blog.formhub.org/2012/10/10/formhub-facilitates-energy-planning-in-liberia"/>
   <updated>2012-10-10T02:42:44+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://blog.formhub.org/2012/10/10/formhub-facilitates-energy-planning-in-liberia</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By Jonathan Cabral, Stephane Keil and Edwin Adkins&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/2012/10/Screen-Shot-2012-10-09-at-10.35.46-PM.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/2012/10/Screen-Shot-2012-10-09-at-10.35.46-PM.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;[/caption]
As a part of an ongoing project to support the Liberian government in energy related data-gathering and planning, three members of the Modi Lab conducted a two-week training in Monrovia to prepare key energy and data specialists from Liberian government, the electric utility, and related energy organizations in the use of mobile rapid data-gathering tools to estimate the urban and rural energy demand in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the end of the civil war in 2003, the Liberian power sector was largely destroyed, leaving less than 1% of Liberia’s population with access to grid electricity.  Most of the country’s population relies upon generation at home, independent power producers (IPP) providing electricity by wire from diesel generators, or, in some smaller cities, limited municipal mini-grids.  Access to modern energy will be a critical element if Liberia is to restart the process of economic and social development.  Since energy needs are urgent and development budgets are limited, an approach is needed that optimizes costs and allows planners to select and prioritize among different generation technologies (grid, solar and diesel, as well as hydro, where available).  Mobile data gathering tools can help to geo-locate homes, facilities, commercial and industrial sites, and IPPs – all of which help to quantify electricity demands and current supply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two weeks, 20 government and utility employees drawn from 4 core partner organizations –&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Ministry of Lands, Mines and Energy (MLME),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Rural and Renewable Energy Agency (RREA),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Liberian Electricity Corporation (LEC),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Liberian Institute of Statistics and Geographic Information Services (LISGIS)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;participated in a practical training with two key tools:  formhub.org (to manage mobile data collection) and Android smartphones running Open Data Kit (ODK), an open-source software for conducting surveys, gathering geographic coordinates, and other media (photos, video) using mobile phones and other devices.  The intensive two week training covered all aspects of using Formhub, the process of writing special syntax into Excel spreadsheets  creating mobile surveys (“authoring”), the use of Android phones to conduct pilot surveys in locations around Monrovia, and finally, the steps to visualize and analyze the information gathered during the training with software such as QGIS (an open-source GIS software package).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/2012/10/Screen-Shot-2012-10-09-at-10.36.31-PM.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/2012/10/Screen-Shot-2012-10-09-at-10.36.31-PM.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The practical nature of the formhub training allowed the government institutions to select a current need for data collection, define the set of questions required to study the issue and pilot the survey, in preparation for a full scale data gathering effort.  During training each organization chose a different data need to fill: RREA designed a survey to understand the cookstove energy needs.  The utility LEC took surveys of potential new grid customers to gauge customer demand in unserved areas.  LISGIS and MLME, both government agencies, collaborated on a survey that profiled and mapped out Independent Power Producers (IPP) serving electrical needs of Monrovian communities at various scales.  The training accommodated versatile needs of each organization with the many features of formhub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was interesting testing the formhub data collection process in a challenging environment.  Typically, many innovations in the field of ICT4D that function great in big US cities commonly fail as soon as one tries them in the developing world context.  We are proud to announce that formhub was successful in proving its functionality under stressful situations of intermittent power and data connectivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All participating institutions were provided with Android smartphones to start piloting their formhub based survey efforts. The utility company will start working right away on their Cross Border Needs Assessment.  This involves a study of 18 communities close to the border with Ivory Coast that will soon have access to power coming from the neighboring countries.  Understanding the power demand of such rural communities will be extremely valuable to parameterize the Earth Institute modeling efforts and improve the accuracy of the different scenarios for the energy grid planning.  The other government ministries and agencies are also rapidly forming working groups to pilot formhub-based data collection projects.  Our group looks forward to supporting the Liberian ministries and utility company as they continue testing and adopting formhub for their data collection needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/2012/10/Screen-Shot-2012-10-09-at-10.35.02-PM.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/2012/10/Screen-Shot-2012-10-09-at-10.35.02-PM.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Using Technology for Education Sector Spatial Planning: Case Study from Ghana  </title>
   <link href="http://blog.formhub.org/2012/09/19/using-technology-for-education-sector-spatial-planning-case-study-from-ghana"/>
   <updated>2012-09-19T02:00:21+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://blog.formhub.org/2012/09/19/using-technology-for-education-sector-spatial-planning-case-study-from-ghana</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Radhika Iyengar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Picture this! I am in a rural District in India. I have been tasked to conduct a situation analysis of Education needs in the district. Sitting in the District Collectors Office (An officer who is in charge of the District’s functioning for all the Sectors). Where do I start? “I need a map of the district” I call out loudly. I am pointed out to a map behind the District Collector’s chair on the wall.  I begin to hand draw the map on a piece of paper.  The same day I leave with the District Education Officer in a Jeep and trying to follow the map. There seems to be some debate over the map (or my drawing) on the boundaries of the District.  Amidst much debate, I try to plot schools on the locations of the schools on the map. In a separate piece of paper, I quickly write down the name of the school and its needs (toilets (Y/N), water availability (Y/N) etc.). School after school I did this, however it is impossible to cover the district because there are more than 200 primary schools in the district that are all spread out.  In the rainy season, few schools are inaccessible due to bad roads and potholes. We come back and I begin searching through DISE (District Information Systems for Education) an online repository of all schools for the District (for the entire country). I begin searching the names of the schools in DISE to the ones that I visit. “There must be something wrong“ I say to myself. I couldn’t find two from the five schools I visited. “Did I write down the right name? “ maybe that school was in this district, but how is this possible?” are some of the thoughts in my head. In some cases the facility inventories did not match what I saw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not an un-usual scenario for Education planners. However things have changed…all due to an innovative use of technology. In my recent visit to an MVP site in Ghana at Bolgatanga. The MVP had recently completed a basic school inventory of all schools in the MVP defined cluster. This survey was conducted using android phones that did not involve data entry at all.  The survey included some of the basic information needed for Education planning such as –water and sanitation, furniture, teacher and teacher training, number of students enrolled etc. Along with this a GPS location of each school and photo of the school was uploaded onto to the server using phones. The data was processed and displayed on maps with school points and a pull down menu of the characteristics of the schools.  This detailed data removed the guess work involved and the anecdotal evidence that an Education planner has to most often rely on.  The snapshots of the MVP cluster maps are given below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/2012/09/Screen-shot-2012-09-18-at-9.57.44-PM.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/2012/09/Screen-shot-2012-09-18-at-9.57.44-PM-1024x538.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We followed the route (in brown) and saw the schools, had an excel sheet with all the data points for the particular schools. The excel sheet with the data points helped to categorize how many schools needed a lot of investments, how many schools needed moderate investments and how many schools needed very little investments, based on the categories that were recorded. However the data in the excel sheet for each school did not give a sense of the need or the coverage of the cluster. The maps were helpful to see the coverage of area with school facilities and the excel sheets with updated data was able to inform the magnitude of the needs. The maps also had population clusters to inform whether a densely populated cluster or village had a school within the proximity.  In a quick look, we were able to see if the population clusters had atleast one school in the cluster. The maps are also useful to observe the coverage of the cluster, therefore maps was useful to tell us if there is a part of the cluster where there are no schools located. In terms of planning, we could assess if there pockets of population where maybe a Kindergarten classes need to be established since the nearest school is more than 4-5 km away. Maps also become a useful platform to engage in discussions with the District Education Office and ask them (without anecdotes) on what visible gaps they can fill and how can MVP supplement. We were able to put all sorts of planning notes on the maps itself to be able to internally discuss with the MVP data team and the Education Sector staff on some data that had to be validated.  At the end of our discussions a round of data validation round was proposed for some specific schools. As for the Education Sector planning, the maps and data helped us to better understand the scope of the Education needs in the cluster and prepare our budgets accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(The Author would like to acknowledge Modi Research lab for making the maps accessible and the MVP MVIG team for the data collection efforts at the site)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Ahora formhub esta disponible en Español!</title>
   <link href="http://blog.formhub.org/2012/09/05/ahora-formhub-esta-disponible-en-espanol"/>
   <updated>2012-09-05T16:33:13+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://blog.formhub.org/2012/09/05/ahora-formhub-esta-disponible-en-espanol</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hemos estado trabajando arduamente en la traducción de nuestra plataforma para la recolección de datos con tecnología móvil a otros idiomas. En formhub creemos firmemente en la cooperación y diseminación gratuita del conocimiento y las herramientas productivas, es muy importante para nosotros que el idioma no sea una barrera para adoptar nuestra tecnología. Existen 500 millones de hispanohablantes nativos en el mundo y es el tercer idioma con mayor numero de hablantes (detrás del Ingles y el Mandarín),  formhub no estaría completo sin los “formhubbers” (termino para designar a los usuarios de formhub) de habla hispana.  formhub ya soportaba la creación de encuestas en múltiples lenguajes usando las capacidades de los teléfonos inteligentes Android, con esta adición nos acercamos a ser completamente multilingües! Esperamos disfrute del sitio en español y le pedimos de favor que nos ayude a mejorar la traducción. Y muy pronto tendremos Formhub traducido al Chino!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Le damos la más cordial bienvenida a formhub!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;formhub Now available in Spanish!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have been working hard to translate our platform for mobile data collection into other languages​​. At formhub, we strongly believe in cooperation and free dissemination of knowledge and productivity tools, it is very important to us that language is not a barrier to adopting our technology. There are 500 million native Spanish speakers in the world and it is the third largest language by number of speakers (after English and Mandarin), formhub would not be complete without the Spanish-speaking &amp;ldquo;formhubbers&amp;rdquo; (term for users Formhub). Formhub already supports survey authoring in multiple languages ​​using the language features of Android smartphones, with this new addition we are close to being completely multilingual! We hope you enjoy the site in Spanish and we ask you to please help us to improve the translation. Soon we will also have formhub translated into Chinese!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to formhub!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>formhub at the DataDev Workshop</title>
   <link href="http://blog.formhub.org/2012/08/31/formhub-at-the-datadev-workshop"/>
   <updated>2012-08-31T04:00:51+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://blog.formhub.org/2012/08/31/formhub-at-the-datadev-workshop</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On July 23rd and 24th we presented a poster on &lt;a href=&quot;https://formhub.org/&quot;&gt;formhub&lt;/a&gt; at the DataDev workshop and participated in the Systems for Mobile Data Collection panel.  The workshop was held during the IEEE Mobile Data Management (MDM 2012) conference in Bangalore India.  Shown below is the poster that we presented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://imgur.com/lmKFh.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Per usual the statistics are out of date, which shows how much formhub is growing (70,000 submissions in 5 weeks) and highlights the inherit evanescence of data, which is one of reasons we built formhub.  Below is a photo of the formhub poster during the demo session at the DataDev workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/2012/08/IMG_20120723_154616.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/2012/08/IMG_20120723_154616-768x1024.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it is hard to see from this picture, we have ODK Collect open on the tablet and a net-book nearby, which we used to walk people through the live site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a lot of great conversations with other solution providers and with practitioners.  There is certainly a great demand for data collection tools and data collection consulting services.  Multiple practitioners wanted a solutions provider that would take them (or their clients) from needs analysis and form creation through data collection all the way to results analysis, recommendations, and impact analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/2012/08/IMG_20120726_124127.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/2012/08/IMG_20120726_124127-1024x768.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While in Bangalore we stopped by &lt;a href=&quot;https://research.microsoft.com/en-us/labs/india/&quot;&gt;Microsoft Research India&lt;/a&gt;.  There is a lot of interesting work involving IVR (interactive voice response) systems coming out of Microsoft Research India, and it has the potential to integrate with formhub, should the need arise.  We also stopped by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thoughtworks.com/&quot;&gt;ThoughtWorks&lt;/a&gt; and discussed possibilities for collaboration on data analysis tools, as with hexbins additional data analysis will be forthcoming in formhub.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>NYC and Nairobi devs connect</title>
   <link href="http://blog.formhub.org/2012/08/30/nyc-and-nairobi-devs-connect"/>
   <updated>2012-08-30T23:40:27+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://blog.formhub.org/2012/08/30/nyc-and-nairobi-devs-connect</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The majority of recent formhub programming has been performed by the development team in Nairobi.  For two weeks in July, part of the New York City formhub development team got a chance to work with the team in Nairobi.  We learned about all the recent additions to formhub from a technical perspective, set some priorities for the future, and &amp;mdash;&amp;ndash; of course &amp;mdash;&amp;ndash; did some coding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/2012/08/nairobi_office_projector.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/2012/08/nairobi_office_projector.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We worked out of a spare classroom, and made ample use of a projector to review code and make architecture decisions &amp;mdash;&amp;ndash; some functions just make more sense when they are life size.  In the photo above, Ukang'a Dickson stands next to the fabfile, figuring out how to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/modilabs/formhub/blob/master/fabfile.py#L60&quot;&gt;deploy a specific branch&lt;/a&gt; with a one liner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course we didn&amp;rsquo;t spend our whole trip coding in front of a projector.  In the photo below we are on top of the Kenyatta Conference Center in downtown Nairobi.  It is the second tallest building in Nairobi, and you can see the Times Tower, the tallest building in Nairobi, right behind us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/2012/08/IMG_20120714_153626.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/2012/08/IMG_20120714_153626.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also during our coding sessions Larry Weya led us through the new export code.  We refactored the existing export code and it now provides a more unified interface for different export formats with all the data coming from a parsed version of the raw XML submissions.  For the end user, this allows formhub to support deletion of individual records, selective processing on export, and other features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/2012/08/Modi_Research_Group_-_CGC_Presentation_-_July_2012.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/2012/08/Modi_Research_Group_-_CGC_Presentation_-_July_2012.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also gave a presentation to the members of the Columbia Global Center in Nairobi, and some guests.  Our presentation included the above and now out of date slide.  204,654 submissions is so last month, as of August 30th 2012 formhub is now at 272,300 submission and counting&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Hexbins!</title>
   <link href="http://blog.formhub.org/2012/08/24/hexbins"/>
   <updated>2012-08-24T19:28:03+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://blog.formhub.org/2012/08/24/hexbins</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Prabhas Pokharel&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this blog post, I want to introduce a feature we&amp;rsquo;ve added to formhub a little while back: spatial summarization using hexagonal bins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of hexagonal binning of 2D space is extremely similar to that of histograms, just extended to 2D space. You take the range of data, split it into several chunks, and compare an aggregation across these chunks. Instead of the line that forms a base of the histogram, we choose hexagonal bins as our &amp;ldquo;chunk,&amp;rdquo; and represent aggregate data using colors rather than height or width. I&amp;rsquo;ll let &lt;a href=&quot;http://indiemaps.com/blog/2011/10/hexbins/&quot;&gt;this &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://indiemaps.com/blog/2011/10/hexbins/&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; do the talking if you are interested in learning more, and move on to examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At formhub, we have enabled two different forms of spatial summarization:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Counts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the most basic (and often most useful) form of summarization, showing the distribution of counts across space. Lets say, in a survey about water points in some area, we want to answer a basic question: what is the distribution of water points across the survey area? While the spatial scatter of the map view already gives us a basic clue, hex bins can alleviate problems overplotting might cause, and give us a glance at this information. On the top-right &amp;ldquo;layers&amp;rdquo; control (&lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/2012/08/Screen-Shot-2012-08-10-at-5.55.11-PM.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://formhub.org/static/css/images/layers.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) , select the &amp;ldquo;Hexbin layer&amp;rdquo; checkbox to see this summarization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/2012/08/Screen-Shot-2012-08-10-at-5.55.11-PM.png&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/2012/08/Screen-Shot-2012-08-10-at-5.55.11-PM.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Proportion of given response(s)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This count-based summarization is quite useful, but easy to do in GIS and other software, particularly because a survey will only produce a single unique count-based summarization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The power of hexbins in formhub is that they allow you to look at your data in a much richer way. In a water point survey, for example, you might care about what proportion of water points within a given area are non-functional. To do that, you would click on &amp;ldquo;View by&amp;rdquo;, find the question whose responses you want to spatially visualize (such as &amp;ldquo;Is the water point functional&amp;rdquo;) and select &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo; in the legend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/2012/08/Screen-Shot-2012-08-10-at-6.00.46-PM.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/2012/08/Screen-Shot-2012-08-10-at-6.00.46-PM.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; What you see, denoted by the intensity of blue in this view, is the percentage of water points that are non-functional in an area. You can in fact go ahead and click on any select-one question in the view-by menu, and select any option to look at how the responses to that questions are spread spatially. We believe this is quite a powerful feature, given that you can choose which response in a particular survey is most valuable to you. In the water points case above, the hexbin density map can practically be used to set the agenda for which areas are in the most need to their water points being fixed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The caveat here is that a deep blue hexagonal bin may represent an area where the only water point is non-functional, or an area where 10 out of 10 water points are non-functional. We made the default coloration proportion rather than count because we think that is more important and hard to derive; we&amp;rsquo;ll add a toggle to color hex bins by &amp;lsquo;the number of non-functional water points in an area&amp;rsquo; when we redesign the map page in the early fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us know what you think of this feature either here in the comments or on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/forum/?fromgroups#!forum/formhub-users&quot;&gt;formhub-users mailing list&lt;/a&gt;, particularly if you come up with interesting uses or insights from the feature. And thanks to github user &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com/indiemaps&quot;&gt;@indiemaps&lt;/a&gt; for contributing &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/indiemaps/hexbin-js/&quot;&gt;the javascript library&lt;/a&gt; that performs much of the heavy lifting for this feature.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>New in formhub...</title>
   <link href="http://blog.formhub.org/2012/08/17/new-in-formhub"/>
   <updated>2012-08-17T20:49:41+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://blog.formhub.org/2012/08/17/new-in-formhub</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;At formhub, we don&amp;rsquo;t have versioned releases. Instead, we follow the &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Continuous_integration&quot;&gt;continuous integration/deployment&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; model. While we deploy updates &lt;a href=&quot;http://timothyfitz.wordpress.com/2009/02/10/continuous-deployment-at-imvu-doing-the-impossible-fifty-times-a-day/&quot;&gt;nearly as frequently as some&lt;/a&gt;, we do push updates quite frequently; often more than once a day. This makes the standard announcement of features per release a little tougher, so I&amp;rsquo;ve tried to start a &amp;ldquo;new in formhub&amp;rdquo; post per week over at &lt;a href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/group/formhub-users&quot;&gt;formhub-users&lt;/a&gt;. Here are the last two:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Posted on Friday, August 17:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;formhub now serves up the media you upload to it properly to ODK collect. For those of your working with media in your forms, the process should become much more seamless now. Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;http://formhub.org/formhub_u/forms/Birds&quot;&gt;Birds form on formhub_u&lt;/a&gt; to see how this works. (adapted from the odk forms &lt;a href=&quot;https://code.google.com/p/opendatakit/source/browse/?repo=forms&quot;&gt;repo&lt;/a&gt;) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A new header and other stylistic changes. We have begun a process of the UI revamp on formhub, and a new header, typography, and other stylistic changes were pushed up this week. Hope you like them!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leaflet upgrade. We upgraded the mapping library we use, leaflet.js to &lt;a href=&quot;http://leaflet.cloudmade.com/2012/07/30/leaflet-0-4-released.html&quot;&gt;0.4&lt;/a&gt;. You may notice a few little changes on the map, like a smoother zoom.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IE 0.9 fix. During the addition of google satellites, we accidentally broke the map view for IE 0.9 users. That has been fixed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data posts to bamboo as they come into formhub working. This will sound cryptic to most. But once our web-data-analysis engine bamboo is released, this feature (continuous updates) will make many of you happier :)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Posted on Friday, August 10:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;formhub can now update an external webservice with data as data is submitted to formhub (see &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.formhub.org/2012/08/06/posting-to-external-site/&quot;&gt;the blogpost&lt;/a&gt; for details)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google Satellite Maps are now available as a background on the map view&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;formhub&amp;rsquo;s xlsform engine now has a &amp;ldquo;hidden&amp;rdquo; field (which only takes a &amp;ldquo;name&amp;rdquo;) which outputs a bind element, and  a space in the instance, but nothing in the body &amp;mdash; this was added for those using formhub as an xform-generation engine to produce xforms for commcare, which makes use of these &amp;lsquo;hidden&amp;rsquo; fields to load case data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;i18n support: formhub now has the infrastructure to support site-wide translations. Those with their &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.w3.org/International/questions/qa-lang-priorities.en.php&quot;&gt;browser locale settings&lt;/a&gt; set to French should already see quite a bit of the site translated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Posting To External Site</title>
   <link href="http://blog.formhub.org/2012/08/06/posting-to-external-site"/>
   <updated>2012-08-06T13:41:07+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://blog.formhub.org/2012/08/06/posting-to-external-site</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve recently worked on a new feature that allows you to have data submissions to a form be pushed to an external site. Currently you can get json and xml data submissions posted to a rest service that can consume it. You may have noticed a new section &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rest Services &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;in the form view. To learn how to make use of these new feature, visit the formhub.org wiki on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/modilabs/formhub/wiki/Posting-To-External-Site&quot;&gt;https://github.com/modilabs/formhub/wiki/Posting-To-External-Site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Cascading Selects</title>
   <link href="http://blog.formhub.org/2012/07/19/cascading-selects"/>
   <updated>2012-07-19T04:50:29+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://blog.formhub.org/2012/07/19/cascading-selects</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Within the &lt;a href=&quot;http://modi.mech.columbia.edu&quot;&gt;Modi Research Group&lt;/a&gt; (informally known as modilabs), we are constantly creating new ways to improve the xlsform-based data collection process. Sometimes we are so busy thinking of new things and implementing them that we don&amp;rsquo;t even announce some of the features we have introduced to make data collection simpler and easier. This time around, I want to talk about cascading-selects, a feature that we introduced into xlsform / formhub a couple of months ago, and which intrepid user Nikolai has dug up and &lt;a href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/d/topic/opendatakit/JHAbgh1kKOs/discussion&quot;&gt;started spreading&lt;/a&gt; around (thanks Nik for forcing us to write this blog post :).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The problem&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Say you want to do data collection, and present the user with a series of selection questions, where the answer depends on a previous selection. The classic example is asking someone to enter a district in a country. But you don&amp;rsquo;t want the user to deal with 777 options at once (example from Nigeria), so you present enumerators with a question asking them about the zone they are in (6 in the country), the state they are in depending no the zone (less than 10 per zone), and then, finally, the LGA, depending on the state they are in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turns out that this is possible with xlsforms without cascading select, but it requires you to write out one question per state in this case (36 different questions), with a fairly complex criteria in the relevant column. And even then, the end information you care about is what zone, state, and LGA the enumerator has filled out information about. Calculating this information requires writing a gigantic if statement, with the same number of branches as there are states in the country! This is quite an unimaginable process, so people have to resort to something like using a different tool for the job, like Kobo Collect. We wanted to make a tool so people could use formhub painlessly and still collect cascading-select information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The feature&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;****Since xlsforms are computer processed, we introduced a feature called cascading-select, where the user is able to simply list the cascading relationships. In a sheet called &lt;code&gt;cascades&lt;/code&gt; the xlsform needs a table like so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;name&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;zone&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;state&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;lga&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;label&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Choose your zone:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Choose your state:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Choose your lga:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;choice_label&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zone 1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;State 1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LGA 1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;choice_label&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zone 1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;State 1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LGA 2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;choice_label&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zone 1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;State 2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LGA 3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;choice_label&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zone 1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;State 2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LGA 4&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;choice_label&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zone 2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;State 3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LGA 5&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;choice_label&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zone 2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;State 3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LGA 6&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;choice_label&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zone 2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;State 4&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LGA 1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;choice_label&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zone 2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;State 4&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LGA 2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in the survey sheet, a simple question like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;type&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;name&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;cascading_select lga&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;mylga&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;will present the user with three questions (which one shows up totally depends on previous input):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/2012/07/2012-07-19_08-39-20.png&quot;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/2012/07/2012-07-19_08-39-20.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/2012/07/2012-07-19_08-39-20-168x300.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/2012/07/2012-07-19_09-58-52.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/2012/07/2012-07-19_09-58-52-168x300.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/2012/07/2012-07-19_08-39-43.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/2012/07/2012-07-19_08-39-43-168x300.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/2012/07/2012-07-19_08-39-43.png&quot;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But underneath the hood, xlsforms will generate 7 different select-one questions (1 for the zone, 2 for the states (per zone), and 4 for the LGAs (per state)), and write the appropriate skip logic to ask them given the right prior selections. [ref] Try it our yourself! Go to &lt;a href=&quot;http://formhub.org/forms&quot;&gt;the forms page on formhub&lt;/a&gt;, search for &amp;ldquo;cascad&quot; , and clone any of the forms that show up there. The one I have worked above is available &lt;a href=&quot;http://formhub.org/pld/forms/cascading_select_test&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://formhub.org/prabhasp/forms/cascading_select_test_cloned&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. [/ref]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And even more, there will be calculations added to the form, so that if you want to know the zone, the state, or the LGA of your submission, you can just look for variables called mylga, mylga_state, and mylga_zone in this case. The &amp;ldquo;mylga&amp;rdquo; bit was obtained from the name assigned to the cascading select, and the &amp;ldquo;state&amp;rdquo; and the &amp;ldquo;zone&amp;rdquo; respectively from the &amp;ldquo;name&amp;rdquo; row in the &amp;ldquo;cascades&amp;rdquo; sheet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/2012/07/Screen-Shot-2012-07-19-at-10.12.27-AM.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/2012/07/Screen-Shot-2012-07-19-at-10.12.27-AM.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above is a simple test case, and may not seem impressive. But when you&amp;rsquo;re dealing with 777 LGAs, like we were in Nigeria, the feature can be a life-saver. The nice bonus is that admin boundary data is stored in a format that corresponds very closely to the cascades sheet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The limitations / the future of cascading-selects&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those intimately familiar with xlsforms will wonder: so we specified the &amp;ldquo;label&quot;s for each of the options above, but where are the &quot;name&quot;s for each of the options? xlsforms derives the names directly from the label, but knocking out capital letters, and replacing all non-alphanumeric with an underscore. This makes the form-authoring convenient, but introduces a major limitation (and perhaps the main reason we haven&amp;rsquo;t been all-drums-blaring about cascading-selects). This automatic name derivation, which departs from the xlsform norm, means that not only are we missing the ability to create custom slugs (such as digit codes for districts), but the multiple language support in the rest of xlsform falls through :( [ref] We do have ideas about how to take cascading selects to a form which supports name/label pairings and multiple languages, so if there is a team out there with developer resources available and wanting to expand this feature, please get in touch with us at support@formhub.org. As always, you can check out (in this case, a possibly hairy) implementation at http://github.com/modilabs/pyxform [/ref].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second limitation is that we use javarosa without itemselects, which means that the xform that ODK collect evaluates contains many many questions with a long menu of options, and a really complex calculation. ODK actually crashed for us at the level of complexity of 777 LGAs in 36 states (although half that number was okay). A better approach might be to use new javarosa itemselects; we haven&amp;rsquo;t explored this path yet, but likely will soon, as ODK Collect 1.2 will soon come out with item-select support..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third limitation is a bug that is easy to get around, but might catch you by surprise. Because the code generates a name based on the label, if you have two states with the same label (but in two different zones), cascading selects won&amp;rsquo;t work properly. It will handle LGAs (i.e., leaf-level options) with the same label in two states, but two states with the same name will cause problems. The solution, if you encounter this, is to change the spelling of one state (adding spaces at the end should suffice, but please do check that it does).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/2012/07/Screen-Shot-2012-07-19-at-10.12.27-AM.png&quot;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>formhub.org in a presentation</title>
   <link href="http://blog.formhub.org/2012/05/08/formhub-org-in-a-presentation"/>
   <updated>2012-05-08T17:25:30+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://blog.formhub.org/2012/05/08/formhub-org-in-a-presentation</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last week, colleagues at the Modi Research Group and I presented the following slides to the MVP (Millennium Villages Project) Colloquium. We wanted to share the presentation with a larger group of formhub.org users, in case you didn&amp;rsquo;t know about some of the features that we have in formhub.org (which are covered in the &amp;ldquo;Beyond the Basics&amp;rdquo; section) and so you know about some of what we are planning for the future of formhub.org and other tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(If the presentation doesn&amp;rsquo;t load above, &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/pub?id=1yh4R5bgqFytIgll8gD6-7u3NaUUm2kNVdxOgGAwVvg0&amp;amp;start=false&amp;amp;loop=false&amp;amp;delayms=3000#slide=id.p16&quot;&gt;please click here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>New Insights from your formhub map</title>
   <link href="http://blog.formhub.org/2012/04/09/new-insights-from-your-formhub-map"/>
   <updated>2012-04-09T16:48:23+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://blog.formhub.org/2012/04/09/new-insights-from-your-formhub-map</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;formhub is designed to make data collection simple and collaborative. But data collection is only a means&amp;hellip; the end goal is gaining insights from data. While formhub cannot provide the rich variety of analysis needed for every dataset, we have been recently been working on features that should give formhub users some basic and rapid insights about data as soon as it is collected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The immediate goals are to allow formhub&amp;rsquo;s users to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Color the map according to responses to select questions. For example, the screenshot below shows our responses to a water questionnaire color coded by responses to a question about &lt;strong&gt;mobile signal strength&lt;/strong&gt; near Port A Piment in Haiti, which shows that signal strength is high (red in this case) only along the coast:&lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/2012/04/formhub-20120409-125331.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/2012/04/formhub-20120409-125331-300x187.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Right now, this feature is enabled for &amp;ldquo;select one&amp;rdquo; questions; we will soon be extending it to numerical and date responses as well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Filter responses on the map by selecting a particular response and a filter criteria&amp;mdash;for example, view all the data where the respondent's age is between 25 and 30. This feature is up and coming; we hope it allows users to explore datasets with large number of datapoints (which may overlap with each other).
    &lt;strong&gt;UPDATE:&lt;/strong&gt; This is now possible: in the legend, you will see that some of the answer-responses appear as a link. Click one of them, and the points on the map will be filtered; only responses that have that particular answer show up. You can also click on multiple items, or click on the link again to remove the filter. See picture below for example:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/2012/04/Screen-Shot-2012-05-04-at-2.00.48-PM.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/2012/04/Screen-Shot-2012-05-04-at-2.00.48-PM-300x138.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Implementation Details&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to develop these features, we have developed an API that allows retrieval of responses via the URL http://formhub.org/&lt;strong&gt;&lt;username&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;/forms/&lt;strong&gt;&lt;form_name&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;/api [ref]  The API is a simple mongodb query API, and is currently meant for formhub&amp;rsquo;s internal use. If you have external use cases for an API, please share your use case with &lt;a href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/forum/?fromgroups/formhub-users#!forum/formhub-users&quot;&gt;formhub-users@googlegroups.com&lt;/a&gt; [/ref]. The API allows data filtrations by passing the name of the response and the value to filter by e.g. gender as the name and male as the filter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have also migrated the map to the open source &lt;a href=&quot;http://leaflet.cloudmade.com/&quot;&gt;Leaflet library&lt;/a&gt;. The Leaflet library includes a number of features that makes it suitable for formhub:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It provides support for a variety of map providers. With this, we have added three maps that are easily switchable from the button on the top right corner i.e. An Open Street Map, a Bing Road Map and a Bing Satelite Map&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It includes out of the box support for the GeoJSON map data format. This allows us to easily modify the map data using client-side javascript.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first item of the analysis goals is now live on the maps.  To use this feature, click on the item labeled &quot;&lt;strong&gt;View By&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;ldquo; on the top right and pick a response to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, any feedback on what we can do to improve these tools will be greatly appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>A new xlsform engine, new documentation, and more!</title>
   <link href="http://blog.formhub.org/2012/02/23/a-new-xlsform-engine-new-documentation-and-more"/>
   <updated>2012-02-23T22:28:03+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://blog.formhub.org/2012/02/23/a-new-xlsform-engine-new-documentation-and-more</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We have been developing on formhub continuously over the past few months, and a couple of weeks ago upgraded the xlsform engine that formhub uses. Along with the new engine, we have also updated formhub documentation and have established a formhub account called &lt;a href=&quot;https://formhub.org/formhub_u&quot;&gt;formhub University&lt;/a&gt; where you can learn how to make xlsforms to do the kind of data collection you need!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;XLSform Upgrade&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;formhub&amp;rsquo;s xlsform engine has been upgraded. Exciting new features include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Upgraded Syntax&lt;/strong&gt;
We have made the syntax for authoring xlsforms simpler. Instead of bind:constraint, you will be writing constraint, and instead of select one from options, you can simply write select_one options. For a preview of the new simplified language, look at our newly updated  &lt;a href=&quot;http://formhub.org/syntax&quot;&gt;syntax page&lt;/a&gt; or view the  &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0AgpC5gsTSm_4dDRVOEprRkVuSFZUWTlvclJ6UFRvdFE&quot;&gt;XLSform standard document&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New Features&lt;/strong&gt;
Along with simplification, we have added some language features that were previously missing, such as the ability to do calculations with xlsforms. See the &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&quot;https://formhub.org/formhub_u/forms/tip_calculator&quot;&gt;Tip Calculator&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; on &lt;a href=&quot;http://formhub.org/formhub_u/&quot;&gt;formhub_u&lt;/a&gt;, for example.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Widgets&lt;/strong&gt;
All ODK 1.1.7 widgets can now be created using the xlsform language. See the &amp;ldquo;ODK 1.1.7 Widgets&amp;rdquo; form on &lt;a href=&quot;http://formhub.org/formhub_u/&quot;&gt;formhub_u&lt;/a&gt; for an example of widgets, and make sure to follow the instructions listed within the description.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The library (which is currently named pyxform and pending rename to xlsform) is at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/modilabs/pyxform&quot;&gt;https://github.com/modilabs/pyxform&lt;/a&gt; if you want to browse the source, fork, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;More Documentation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As referenced above, we have updated the formhub &lt;a href=&quot;http://formhub.org/syntax&quot;&gt;syntax page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have also added a &lt;a href=&quot;http://formhub.org/formhub_u/&quot;&gt;formhub_u account on formhub&lt;/a&gt;, where there are surveys that teach you how to write many different kinds of forms:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://formhub.org/formhub_u/forms/xlsform_blank&quot;&gt;A survey template&lt;/a&gt; makes it easier to write new forms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://formhub.org/formhub_u/forms/tutorial&quot;&gt;An updated tutorial&lt;/a&gt; should get you started quickly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://formhub.org/formhub_u/forms/tip_calculator&quot;&gt;Tip Calculator&lt;/a&gt; shows you how to do calculations and outputs in forms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://formhub.org/mberg/forms/expense_report&quot;&gt;Expense Report&lt;/a&gt; is an improved version of the expense report form that Matt blogged about on this site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://formhub.org/formhub_u/forms/nutrition_screening&quot;&gt;Child Nutrition Screening Day&lt;/a&gt; was developed at a training in WHO, and shows a fairly complex real-life example.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And finally, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://formhub.org/formhub_u/forms/widgets&quot;&gt;ODK 1.1.7 Widgets&lt;/a&gt; showcases how to make all the new widgets in ODK 1.1.7, and produces the screens from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendatakit.org/help/form-design/examples/&quot;&gt;ODK widget examples&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;And the features&amp;hellip; they keep coming!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have also been constantly adding new features. We will cover a few of these in future blog posts, but a quick list for anyone who has been waiting are below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Media storage in S3 and photo viewing through a galleria plug-in&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;ODK Collect authentication support&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Licensing options for forms and shared data&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Support for webforms (preview your survey or do collection on the web)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deployment scripts to make the deployment of your own formhub server easier.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>New licensing options available both for forms and data</title>
   <link href="http://blog.formhub.org/2012/01/31/form-data-licensing"/>
   <updated>2012-01-31T07:10:20+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://blog.formhub.org/2012/01/31/form-data-licensing</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons we&amp;rsquo;re excited about formhub is that it provides the opportunity to help educate people on best practices regarding both content and data sharing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today we just added the option to select a license for both your forms and data.  The options are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Forms&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No Licensing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/&quot;&gt;Attribution CC BY&lt;/a&gt; - Ability to share, remix, make commercial use of the work but you must properly attribute as specified by the author or licensor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/&quot;&gt;Attribution-ShareAlike CC BY-SA&lt;/a&gt; - Same as above but of you alter, transform, or build upon this work, you must distribute the resulting work under the same license.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No Licensing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendatacommons.org/licenses/pddl/summary/&quot;&gt;Public Domain Dedication and License 1.0 (PDDL)&lt;/a&gt; - You are free to share, create or adapt the the data with no restriction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendatacommons.org/licenses/by/summary/&quot;&gt;ODC Attribution (ODC-BY)&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; Same as PDDL but you must attribute any public use of the database, or works produced from the database, in the manner specified in the license.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendatacommons.org/licenses/odbl/summary/&quot;&gt;ODC Open Database License (ODBL)&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash;  Same as PDDL but you must attribute, share-alike and keep open.   This is the license &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.openstreetmap.org/&quot;&gt;Open Street Map (OSM)&lt;/a&gt; uses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We encourage you to consider these options if you chose to share your forms or data either through formhub or other means.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>New Features! Making data collection more collaborative and social</title>
   <link href="http://blog.formhub.org/2012/01/29/formhub-now-social"/>
   <updated>2012-01-29T15:26:44+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://blog.formhub.org/2012/01/29/formhub-now-social</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re excited to announce the release of a major new set of features to formhub.  With these updates, we have not only made mobile data collection even easier, but we&amp;rsquo;ve started to introduce the elements that will make data collection more collaborative and even social.  Namely, with formhub you can now easily share forms and publish data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each formhub user, or formhubber as we like to say ;&amp;ndash;), now has their own &lt;a href=&quot;https://formhub.org/mberg&quot;&gt;public profile pag&lt;/a&gt;e that displays any XLSForms or data sets that the user has chosen to share.  Each shared form/data set also has it&amp;rsquo;s own &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.formhub.org/mberg/forms/good_eats&quot;&gt;dedicated page&lt;/a&gt; from which you can view a description of the form, download the original XLSForm used to author the form (if form is shared), export the data in excel, csv or KML (if data is shared) and view a dedicated interactive web map if the form data contains GPS points.   When logged in, the owner of the form can now edit the tile and description of their form and share their XLSForm or data with a flip of a switch.   By default all forms and data are private.  It&amp;rsquo;s completely up to you to share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/2012/01/Screen-Shot-2012-01-29-at-5.57.20-PM.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/2012/01/Screen-Shot-2012-01-29-at-5.57.20-PM.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;formhub User&amp;rsquo;s Public Profile Page&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make discovery of new forms possible, we&amp;rsquo;ve introduced a &lt;a href=&quot;https://formhub.org/forms&quot;&gt;form gallery&lt;/a&gt; that lists all shared forms and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://formhub.org/people&quot;&gt;searchable directory&lt;/a&gt; of other formhubbers using the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we take data privacy and security very seriously,  you can now access access your account and submit data over https with 256 bit SSL encryption.   To benefit from this please access your account via &lt;a href=&quot;https://formhub.org&quot;&gt;https://formhub.org&lt;/a&gt; and switch your server settings accordingly on your phone. &lt;em&gt;Note: this required using ODK Collect 1.1.7.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope you like these new changes and welcome all feedback.   If you signed up for formhub in our early days, we encourage you to come back and have another look!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary of new features &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dedicated &lt;a href=&quot;https://formhub.org/mberg&quot;&gt;personal page profile&lt;/a&gt; with ability to add basic profile information and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gravatar.com&quot;&gt;gravatar&lt;/a&gt; support&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://formhub.org/forms&quot;&gt;Form Gallery&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash;  Browse data collection forms others have shared in the form gallery&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://formhub.org/people&quot;&gt;People directory&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; Meet other formhubbers&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ability to rename forms and give them a description&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ability to easily share or hide forms and form data&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Support to upload XLSforms from external URLs&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;KML exports&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Improved Excel and CSV  export support for repeats in forms&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dedicated &lt;a href=&quot;http://formhub.org/mberg/forms/good_eats/map&quot;&gt;map pages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other features coming soon&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Image thumb-nailing and media storage in S3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;ODK Collect authentication support&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Better support for versioning of forms&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Licensing options for forms and shared data&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Improved handling of labels on exports.  R  and other statistical package support.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Implementation of finalized XLSForm standard (reconciles differences between formhub and ODK XLS2XForm standards).  These additions will allow for full implementation of &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendatakit.org/help/form-design/examples/&quot;&gt;ODK Collect 1.1.7 widgets&lt;/a&gt; including multi-media support.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Support for webforms (preview your survey or do collection on the web)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;View form data in tables&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Built in statistical analysis with vizualizations&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Improved documentation on authoring forms&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deployment scripts to make the deployment of your own formhub server easier.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;OSM map support!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Staying Even - How to use formhub and ODK Collect to track your travel expenses</title>
   <link href="http://blog.formhub.org/2011/12/09/staying-even-how-to-use-formhub-and-odk-collect-to-track-your-travel-expenses"/>
   <updated>2011-12-09T23:56:37+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://blog.formhub.org/2011/12/09/staying-even-how-to-use-formhub-and-odk-collect-to-track-your-travel-expenses</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I travel a LOT and like most people who do struggle to keep track of my reimbursable travel expenses. My memory blurs between trips and I forget about all the cab rides where I don&amp;rsquo;t bother to get a receipt.  As a result, whenever, I get around to finally filing an expense report (the bane of my existence) it usually consists of the big ticket items with receipts that didn’t erase themselves.  Long story short, the cost of me being lazy and unorganized adds up.
&lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/2011/12/Screen-Shot-2011-12-09-at-6.49.17-PM.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/2011/12/Screen-Shot-2011-12-09-at-6.49.17-PM.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I thought I’d try keeping track of my expenses on my android phone (cause it’s always on me) using &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendatakit.org/&quot;&gt;ODK Collect&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.formhub.org&quot;&gt;formhub&lt;/a&gt;. I know there are a ton of travel expense apps out there but the idea of being able to tailor the content to my particular needs: foreign currency, rickshaw rides&amp;hellip; appealed to me. So far it’s been working pretty well for me and here’s what I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I designed the following expense report form in excel (&lt;a href=&quot;https://formhub.org/mberg/forms/expense_report/form.xls&quot;&gt;expense_report.xls&lt;/a&gt;).  It’s very straightforward consisting of things like the expense type, description, amount and currency with the option of taking a photo for the receipt (or activity) and GPS of the location (if I really want to go back and find that kebab stand). I then upload it to my formhub account, which allows me to access it ODK Collect on my phone when I need it.  For detailed instructions on how to do this see &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.formhub.org/tutorial&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.   When I’m done with a trip, I get a clean export of my expenses in excel in the format I defined and if I log the location, I can even see where I traveled on a map which is kind of fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Customizing for my trips&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since excel is so easy to modify, I usually customize my &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/pub?hl=en_US&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;key=0AgpC5gsTSm_4dGxDOXpSdGwtUlVvLVY1TWZ1VzVmS0E&amp;amp;output=xls&quot;&gt;expense report template&lt;/a&gt; to tailor it to my upcoming trip.  For example, I add or remove things like currencies I need on a trip. If my trip is domestic, I usually remove the currency question all together as I know I’ll only be spending dollars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another nifty trick, is to rename the name of the excel form before uploading to reflect the name of the trip.  For example, ER_ghana_nov11.xls. This allows me to easily keep my expenses segregated between trips and a nice historical record of my trips in my formhub account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/2011/12/Screen-Shot-2011-12-09-at-6.44.46-PM.png&quot;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/2011/12/Screen-Shot-2011-12-09-at-6.44.46-PM.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/2011/12/Screen-Shot-2011-12-09-at-6.44.46-PM.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DIY Data Apps&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I really like about this setup is that I can quickly develop a pretty robust data collection app suited to my exact needs. On my phone,  I only need to install a single app providing me a consistent interface that I like and all my data is stored in a data format I define safely online and not on my phone which can be lost or stolen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plus, if someone else comes up with a cool app idea, I can just grab their XLSForm and use/adapt it myself. All this has got me thinking about that street meat map, I want to make!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Data Gatherers of the World Unite!</title>
   <link href="http://blog.formhub.org/2011/12/05/data-gatherers-of-the-world-unite"/>
   <updated>2011-12-05T13:55:23+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://blog.formhub.org/2011/12/05/data-gatherers-of-the-world-unite</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are really excited to announce the beta release of &lt;a href=&quot;http://formhub.org&quot;&gt;formhub&lt;/a&gt;, a service for making data collection &lt;strong&gt;simpler&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;more collaborative&lt;/strong&gt;. Great projects like the Open Data Kit (ODK) project have provided us with very simple tools to collect data, but the process of authoring surveys and going from survey specification to data has always been cumbersome, and accessible only to highly technical users. formhub aims to make the whole data collection process simpler and more collaborative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;formhub makes data collection &lt;strong&gt;simpler&lt;/strong&gt; by making survey authoring simpler, and by providing a hosted site in which going from authored survey to data is quick and painless. formhub has already been used to collect data for more than 12,000 surveys, and the process that inspired formhub was used to collect data on more than 30,000 facilities, so we know it works at scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;formhub also makes data collection &lt;strong&gt;more collaborative&lt;/strong&gt; by working with a human-readable format for authoring xform-based surveys. This new format, XLSform, is based on an underlying excel file, which anyone with access to Microsoft Office, LibreOffice, or Google Docs can edit. Being both human-accessible and machine-readable also makes XLSforms an ideal format with which to share survey specifications once surveys have been fully vetted and authored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The XLSForm Standard&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of our work at the Modi Research Group involves building large complex forms for surveys that often involve hundreds of questions, need to be available in multiple languages, and need to be vetted by multiple people in multiple teams. To help with this process, one of our engineers, Andrew Marder, came up with a way to author the forms in Excel (we then convert them into XForms using a tool called XLS2XForm). We found that web-based form builders were great for building simple forms but were cumbersome as the size and complexity of forms grew. Machine-interpretable surveys in excel files, on the other hand, enabled us to use great tools like Google Docs, Microsoft Excel, and dropbox to manage our surveys. These excel files allowed us to share forms and get feedback from multiple non-technical teams. The excel files are easy to interpret, easy to edit, and thanks to Google Docs extremely easy to collaborate on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Human Readable&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re excited by the XLSForms because we feel they are both machine and human readable, and we hope they can be viable standard for sharing data collection tools.  The xform, which was designed to do this, allows for great interoperability between machine systems but is almost impossible for normal people to read.  As a result, forms are shared in PDF or Microsoft Word-based formats, which can’t easily be converted into a digital data collection process. With XLSForms, you get surveys that are readable with a human eye, as well as by machines. This makes them an ideal format for sharing: as people collaborate over survey design, or once the survey is designed and the need to share with additional partners or the public at large (in a re-usable format) arises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;See what we mean about readability? (Pictures are parts of xform and xlsform specifying the same survey).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/Rf7ZectmEC51EVsNfMyhIPyuhytE07PnITBdLxvwb1wEkFSUSoYgNP3OO6439Ho7-qS1WdmFEjY2l-DwmzAW_YUn34yg1dt1rowCnoTQXmV7kuxVH5I&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/ynVVTqMxoV28vLMR0X1KNcQTSSYNLEQOyy3-U6OGMzkMIF-5oSER9IKjycLO8yv21f65FEkZsZ_e6n07-C6zpYZdz5yT-0eeSHsFYtjUF3s1aSazHJo&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Shareable&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We built formhub around the idea of sharing forms. Sharing forms during survey design, the first point of need for sharing can be done using email and Google Docs. But once a survey is ready and published on formhub, we want to allow survey designers to share their data collection tools with the public or partners they collaborate with. One of the most exciting features on formhub will be this feature—to be able to share an XLSform (an excel file) which has been published as a survey. We don’t have this sharing feature ready yet, but its coming, and we couldn’t be more excited about building it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Simple End-to-End Data Collection&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to allowing everyone to use an easy to share and collaborate medium for defining surveys, formhub allows painless deployment of data collection efforts. The process for deploying a survey through formhub is very simple, and no technical setup knowledge is required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The survey deployer simply:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;signs up for an account&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;writes a survey in the XLSform format&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;submits the XLSform to formhub&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On the data collection side, the data collectors can leverage ODK’s workflow, and simply need to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;configure ODK’s server preferences to point to the appropriate formhub username&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;download the appropriate form&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;conduct the survey&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and submit the data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The data is then immediately available for viewing on a google map or for download from formhub as CSV or Excel files. In demonstrations and trainings, new users have been able to sign up for an account, write simple surveys, deploy them, and get incoming data in a span of minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have a half an hour to spend, we suggest you to try it yourself!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;formhub in Five Words&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope formhub becomes the &lt;em&gt;hub&lt;/em&gt; of your &lt;em&gt;mobile data collection needs&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simple.&lt;/strong&gt;
All you need to get started is an account on formhub, and an ability to author .xls files. There is absolutely no technical setup required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaborative.&lt;/strong&gt;
The format that formhub uses, XLSForm, were designed with collaboration in mind. It allows multiple authors to work on the same survey, but even more, once the survey is designed, for survey authors to share their surveys with the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By enabling the sharing of forms, we hope to foster a collaborative community of data collectors. In many ways, sharing data collection instruments equates to sharing best practices. The standardization of particular forms promotes data standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Secure.&lt;/strong&gt;
We want to provide a safe and secure (https coming soon) place for your data.  We’re working to make sure all data will be backed up in the cloud. At anytime you can easily export your data in excel or CSV formats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Free (as in beer).&lt;/strong&gt;
Our goal is to provide a free (as in beer) service (no question or submission limits) to allow you to publish a form to a phone and begin collecting data. We aim to keep this service free to not limit access to this service. If eventually our hosting costs get unsustainable we’ll work with the community of users to figure out a way forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Free (as in speech).&lt;/strong&gt;
The underlying code for formhub is&lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com/modilabs/formhub&quot;&gt; freely available&lt;/a&gt; under an opensource license.  We wanted to make it easy to host your own formhub instance if you like and if you’re a developer we’d welcome code contributions.  We built formhub in Python and Django since that’s what we’re comfortable using.  If you like Java there are other excellent back-ends available like&lt;a href=&quot;http://opendatakit.org/use/aggregate/&quot;&gt; ODK Aggregate&lt;/a&gt; that we encourage you to checkout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;And Finally, Some Caveats&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please mind the bumps. This is a work in progress but we’ll endeavor to keep your data safe. We are still working on some core features like sharing, but wanted to get the tool out as its already quite useful!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can help by providing feedback, ideas for features, reports of bugs and of course compliments!   Knowing we’re providing a helpful tool is what keeps us going.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Google Docs, Bootstrap, and Django</title>
   <link href="http://blog.formhub.org/2011/10/20/google-docs-bootstrap-and-django"/>
   <updated>2011-10-20T14:21:49+05:30</updated>
   <id>http://blog.formhub.org/2011/10/20/google-docs-bootstrap-and-django</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Andrew Marder&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing good documentation quickly is a hard. Sphinx is great at auto-generating documentation from code, but it&amp;rsquo;s slow to write additional documentation in reStructuredText and not everyone is comfortable writing with a markup language. To work around this barrier to entry we decided to write some of our documentation using Google Docs, then using some features of Django we were able to incorporate the living document directly into our site. Here is the before and after comparison:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/pub?id=1Dze4IZGr0IoIFuFAI_ohKR5mYUt4IAn5Y-uCJmnv1FQ#h.92ndqcrwx98v&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/modilabs/formhub/wiki/images/input.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/modilabs/formhub/wiki/images/output.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or see it in action here: &lt;a href=&quot;http://formhub.org/syntax/&quot;&gt;http://formhub.org/syntax/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some tidbits I found interesting when making this tool:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google Docs uses peculiar section IDs. Instead of using &amp;lsquo;h.92ndqcrwx98v&amp;rsquo; I decided &amp;lsquo;introduction&amp;rsquo; would make a prettier link.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google Docs fakes unordered lists and nested lists. For some reason, the HTML export of the document doesn&amp;rsquo;t have the prettiest HTML. I was particularly frustrated that when I nest one list inside of another the HTML version ends up have three lists one after another with special formatting to make it look like they are nested.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The tables worked out quite well. Some information is lost, but the column widths are fairly well preserved and this will save a ton of time formatting because formatting a Google Doc table is way easier than formatting an HTML table.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It would be nice to have the table of contents float on the right side of the page. Unfortunately, this feature doesn&amp;rsquo;t come out of the box with Twitter Bootstrap, so if anyone knows an easy way to make this happen, please let us know.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re curious to see how this works, check out the code &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/modilabs/formhub/blob/master/main/views/google_doc.py&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;rsquo;ve commented it heavily to explain how everything works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrew Marder&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>